{
  "reference_number": "9281",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": "It is time to get serious about this, be ambitious as a country and get started on the necessary changes."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Long-Lived Gases and Stabilised Short-Lived Gases - Long-lived gases to net zero by 2050 while also stabilising short-lived gases",
      "answer_index": 12,
      "notes": "My understanding is that this option is what is necessary to reduce projected climate disruption. A strong science-based approach\n\n should be taken to ensure that targets are both appropriate and visionary. The agricultural sector should not be exempted from the\n process but should not be penalised in ways that are not contributing to the overall goal."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "Aotearoa New Zealand should take responsibility for its own emissions. We can see the effects of assuming that other countries will\n deal with our solid waste with the piles of recycling plastic now sitting around. We should acknowledge and deal with our own\n\n emissions."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Only under exceptional circumstances, for example the best science available indicating that alternative strategies may differ from\n what is currently understood. Financial considerations are not enough to change the target."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Only under exceptional circumstances, such as a significant natural disaster."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Only under exceptional circumstances, such as a significant natural disaster. Perhaps in this circumstance the banking/borrowing\n from the following budget concept could come into play."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Financial concerns should not be allowed to take priority over the environment."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "The Governmentâ€™s policy plans to meet emission budgets should be comprehensive, fair, cost-effective, environmentally sustainable,\nand reflect a commitment to Te Tiriti o Waitangi."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "I support the CCC being an independent body of experts advising and monitoring progress towards the goal."
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Advising the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 6,
      "notes": "Independence is a valuable attribute to maintain, thereby making decision making more appropriately undertaken by government,\n\nwho are directly accountable to the public."
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Adding public health expertise to the list would be beneficial."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "This is a reality we need to face and it seems this is an appropriate body to deal with it."
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "This is an exciting piece of proposed legislation. We know there are significant and severe implications of anthropogenic climate\n\ndisruption. It would be fantastic to see New Zealand leading the way with an ambitious target with detailed and sensible plans to aid\nus to meet that target. I am truly looking forward to this being passed - something for our country to be proud of as we take steps to\n\nacknowledge what has happened and change the current trajectory."
    }
  ]
}
